<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc.dtd"-->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc docName="draft-ietf-justfont-toplevel-current" category="std" ipr='trust200902'>
<front>
<title>The font Top Level Type </title>
<author initials="C" surname="Lilley" fullname="Chris Lilley">
  <organization>W3C</organization>
  <address>
  <postal>
  	<street>2004 Route des Lucioles</street>
  	<city>Sophia Antipolis</city>
  	<code>06902</code>
  	<country>France</country>
  	</postal>
  	<email>chris@w3.org</email>
  </address>
</author>
<date day="25" month="October" year="2016"/>
<keyword>Internet Media Types</keyword>
<abstract>
 <t>
      This memo serves to register and document the <spanx style="verb">font</spanx> Top Level Type,
      under which the Internet Media subtypes for representation formats for fonts may be registered. This
      document also serves as a registration application for a set of intended subtypes,
      which are representative of some existing subtypes already in use, and currently registered 
      under the "application" tree by their separate registrations.
    </t>
</abstract>
</front>
<middle>

<section title="Specification Development" anchor="issues">
  <t>
[Note to the RFC Editor: Please remove this section upon publication.]
	</t>
	<t>This section is non-normative. The source for this specification is
	<eref target="https://github.com/svgeesus/ietf-justfont">maintained on GitHub</eref>.

  The <eref target="https://github.com/svgeesus/ietf-justfont/issues">issues list</eref> is also on GitHub.

	Discussion should be on the mailing list <eref target="mailto:justfont@ietf.org">justfont@ietf.org</eref>.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
    <t>
      The process of setting type in computer systems and other forms of text presentation
      systems uses fonts in order to provide visual representations of the glyphs. Just as
      with images, for example, there are a number of ways to represent the visual information
      of the glyphs. Early font formats often used bitmaps, as these could have been carefully
      tuned for maximum readability at a given size on low-resolution displays. More recently,
      scalable vector outline fonts have come into widespread use: in these fonts, the
      outlines of the glyphs are described, and the presentation system renders the outline in
      the desired position and size.</t>
    <t>
    Over time, a number of standard formats for recording font
    descriptions have evolved.  
      This document defines a new top-level Internet Media Type "font" according to Section 4.2.7
	  of <xref target="RFC6838"/>. This top-level type indicates that the content specifies
	  font data. Under this top-level type, different representation formats of fonts may be
	  registered.</t>
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
      RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
</section>
<section title="Background and Justification">
    <t>Historically there has not been a registration of formats for fonts. More recently, there
      have been several representation formats registered as media subtypes under the "application"
      top-level type (for example, application/font-woff).  
      However, with the rapid adoption of web fonts (based on the data
      from HTTP Archive <xref target="HTTP-Archive-Trends"/>
      showing a huge increase in web font usage from 1% in the end of 2010
      to 50% across all sites in the beginning of 2015) custom fonts on the web have become
      a core web resource. As the in-depth analysis <xref target="Font-Media-Type-Analysis"/> shows,
      the lack of
      the intuitive top-level font type is causing significant confusion among developers - while
      currently defined font subtypes are severely under-utilized there are many more sites that
      already use non-existent (but highly intuitive) media types such as "font/woff", "font/ttf" and
      "font/truetype". At the same time, the majority of sites resort to using generic types such as
      "application/octet-stream", "text/plain" and "text/html"; or use unregistrable types
      such as "application/x-font-ttf".</t>

    <t>Contrary to the expectations of the W3C WebFonts Working Group which developed WOFF, 
      the officially defined IANA subtypes such as "application/font-woff"
      and "application/font-sfnt" see a very limited use - their adoption rates trail far behind as the
      actual use of web fonts continues to increase. The members of the W3C WebFonts WG concluded that
      the use of "application" top-level type is not ideal. First, the "application" sub-tree is treated
      (correctly) with great caution with respect to viruses and other active code. Secondly, the lack
      of a top-level type means that there is no opportunity to have a common set of optional parameters,
      such as are specified here. Third, fonts have a unique set of licensing and usage restrictions,
      which makes it worthwhile to identify this general category with a unique top-level type.</t>

    <t>The W3C WebFonts WG decided <xref target="WG-tlt"/> that the situation can be significantly improved if a set of font
      media types is registered using "font" as a dedicated top-level type. Based on the data analysis
      presented above, we conclude that it is the presence of simple and highly intuitive media types
      for images that caused their widespread adoption, where the correct
      usage of existing media types reaches over 97% for all subtypes in the "image" tree. The WG
      considers that, considering a rapid adoption of fonts on the web, the registration of the top-level
      media type for fonts along with the intuitive set of subtypes that reflect popular and widely used
      data formats would further stimulate the adoption of web fonts, significantly simplify web server
      configuration process and facilitate the proper use of IANA media type recommendations.</t>
</section>
<section title="Security Considerations">
    <t>Fonts are interpreted data structures that represent collections of different tables containing
      data that represent different types of information, including glyph outlines in various formats,
      hinting instructions, metrics and layout information for multiple languages and writing systems,
      rules for glyph substitution and positioning, etc. 
      
      In particular, the hinting instructions for TrueType glyphs represent executable code which has 
      the potential to be maliciously constructed (for example, intended to hang the interpreter).
      
      There are many existing, already standardized font table tags
      and formats that allow an unspecified number of entries containing predefined data fields for
      storage of variable length binary data. Many existing font formats (TrueType 
      <xref target="truetype-wiki"/>, OpenType
       and OFF <xref target="opentype-wiki"/>, SIL Graphite,
      WOFF, etc.) are based on the table-based SFNT (scalable font) format which is extremely
      flexible, highly extensible and offers an opportunity to introduce additional table structures when
      needed, in an upward-compatible way that would not affect existing font rendering engines and text layout implementations.
      However, this very extensibility may present specific security concerns – the flexibility and ease
      of adding new data structures makes it easy for any arbitrary data to be hidden inside a font file.
      There is a significant risk that the flexibility of font data structures may be exploited to hide
      malicious binary content disguised as a font data component.</t>

    <t>Fonts may contain 'hints', which are programmatic instructions that are executed by the font engine
      for the alignment of graphical elements of glyph outlines with the target display pixel grid.
      Depending on the font technology utilized in the creation of a font these hints may represent active
      code interpreted and executed by the font rasterizer. Even though hints operate within the confines
      of the glyph outline conversion system and have no access outside the font rendering engine, hint
      instructions can be, however, quite complex, and a maliciously designed complex font could cause
      undue resource consumption (e.g. memory or CPU cycles) on a machine interpreting it. Indeed, fonts
      are sufficiently complex that most (if not all) interpreters cannot be completely protected from
      malicious fonts without undue performance penalties.</t>

    <t>Widespread use of fonts as necessary components of visual content presentation warrants that
      careful attention should be given to security considerations whenever a font is either embedded
      into an electronic document or transmitted alongside media content as a linked resource. While
      many existing font formats provide certain levels of protection of data integrity (such mechanisms
      include e.g. checksums and digital signatures), font data formats provide neither privacy nor
      confidentiality protection internally; if needed, such protection should be provided externally.</t>
  </section>
  <section title="IANA Considerations ">
  <t>This specification registers a new top-level type, "font", in the
   standards tree; adds it as an alternative value of "Type Name" in the
   media types registration form  <xref target="Media-Type-Registration"/>; and
   registers several subtypes for it.
  </t>

<section title="Definition and Encoding">
    <t>The "font" as the primary media content type indicates that the content identified by it requires
      certain graphic subsystem such as font rendering engine (and, in some cases, text layout and shaping
      engine) to process it as font data, which in turn may require certain level of hardware capabilities such
      as certain levels of CPU performance and available memory. The "font" media type does not provide
      any specific information about the underlying data format and how the font information should be
      interpreted - the subtypes defined within a "font" tree name the specific font formats.
      Unrecognized sub-types of "font" should be treated as "application/octet-stream". Implementations
      may pass unrecognized subtypes to a common font-handling system, if such a system is available.</t>
  </section>
<section title="Subtype Registrations">
    <t>In this section the initial entries under the top-level 'font' media type are specified. They also
      serve as examples for future registrations.</t>
    <t>For each subtype, an @font-face format identifer is defined. This is for use with the @font-face
    src descriptor, defined by the CSS3 Fonts specification <xref target="W3C.CR-css-fonts-3-20131003"/>.</t>

  <section title="Generic SFNT Font Type">
  <t>
  <list style="hanging">
    <t hangText="Type name:">font</t>
    <t hangText="Subtype name:">sfnt</t>
    <t hangText="Required parameters:">None.</t>
    <t hangText="Optional parameters:">
      <list style="hanging">
    	<t hangText="1) Name: outlines">Value: TTF, CFF, SVG <vspace blankLines="1" />
  	This parameter can be used to specify the type of outlines provided by the font.
      Value "TTF" shall be used when a font resource contains glyph outlines in TrueType
      format, value "CFF" shall be used to identify fonts containing PostScript/CFF outlines <xref target="postscript-wiki"/>,
      and value SVG <xref target="svg-wiki"/>shall be used to identify fonts that include SVG outlines. TTF, CFF
      or SVG outlines can be present in various combinations in the same font file, therefore,
      this optional parameter is a list containing one or more items, separated by commas, with
      optional whitespace. Order in the list is not significant.</t>

    <t hangText="2) Name: layout"></t>
    <t>Value: OTL, AAT, SIL <vspace blankLines="1" />
      This parameter identifies the type of implemented support for advanced text layout
      features. The predefined values "OTL", "AAT" and "SIL" respectively indicate support
      for OpenType text layout, Apple Advanced Typography or Graphite SIL. More than one
      shaping and layout mechanism may be provided by the same font file, therefore,
      this optional parameter is a list containing one or more items, separated by commas, with
      optional whitespace. Order in the list is not significant.</t>
   </list></t>

   <t hangText="Encoding considerations:">Binary.</t>

    <t hangText="Interoperability considerations:">As it was noted in the first paragraph of
    the "Security considerations" section, the same font
      format wrapper can be used to encode fonts with different types of glyph data represented as
      either TrueType or PostScript (CFF) outlines. Existing font rendering engines may not be able
      to process some of the particular outline formats, and downloading a font resource that contains
      unsupported glyph data format would result in inability of application to render and display text.
      Therefore, it would be extremely useful to clearly identify the format of the glyph outline data
      within a font using an optional parameter, and allow applications to make decisions about
      downloading a particular font resource sooner. Similar, another optional parameter is suggested
      to identify the type of text shaping and layout mechanism that is provided by a font. Please
      note that as new outline formats and text shaping mechanisms may be defined in the future, the
      set of allowed values for two optional parameters defined by this section may be extended.</t>

    <t hangText="Published specification:">ISO/IEC 14496-22 "Open Font Format" (OFF) specification
    <xref target="ISO.14496-22.2015"/> being developed by ISO/IEC SC29/WG11.</t>

    <t hangText="Applications that use this media type:">Any and all applications that are able to create, edit or display textual media content.</t>

  <t hangText="Additional information:">

  <list style="hanging">

      <t hangText="Magic number(s):">The TrueType fonts and OFF / OpenType fonts containing TrueType outlines should use 0x00010000
        as the 'sfnt' version number.<vspace blankLines="1" />
      The OFF / OpenType fonts containing CFF data should use the tag 'OTTO' as 'sfnt' version number.</t>

      <t hangText="File extension(s):">Font file extensions used for OFF / OpenType fonts: .ttf, .otf<vspace blankLines="1" />
      Typically, .ttf extension is only used for fonts containing TrueType outlines, while .otf
        extension can be used for any OpenType/OFF font, either with TrueType or CFF outlines.</t>

    <t hangText="Macintosh file type code(s):">(no code specified)</t>
    <t hangText="@font-face Format:">none.</t>
    <t hangText="Fragment Identifiers">none.</t>
    <t hangText="Deprecated Alias:">The existing registration application/font-sfnt is 
    deprecated in favor of font/sfnt.</t>
  </list>
  </t>

    <t hangText="Person &amp; email address to contact for further information:">Vladimir Levantovsky (vladimir.levantovsky@monotype.com).</t>

    <t hangText="Intended usage:">COMMON</t>

    <t hangText="Restrictions on usage:">None</t>

    <t hangText="Author:">The ISO/IEC 14496-22 "Open Font Format" specification is a
    product of the ISO/IEC JTC1 SC29/WG11.</t>

    <t hangText="Change controller:">The ISO/IEC has change control over this specification.</t>

  </list>
  </t>
  </section>


  <section title="TTF Font Type">
  <t>
  <list style="hanging">
    <t hangText="Type name:">font</t>
    <t hangText="Subtype name:">ttf</t>
    <t hangText="Required parameters:">None.</t>

  <t hangText="Optional parameters:">
    <list style="hanging">

    <t hangText="Name: layout">Value: OTL, AAT, SIL<vspace blankLines="1" />

      This parameter identifies the type of support mechanism for advanced text layout
      features. The predefined values "OTL", "AAT" and "SIL" respectively indicate support
      for OpenType text layout, Apple Advanced Typography or Graphite SIL. More than one
      shaping and layout mechanism may be provided by the same font file, therefore,
      this optional parameter is a list containing one or more items, separated by commas, with
      optional whitespace. Order in the list is not significant.</t>
      </list>
      </t>

   <t hangText="Encoding considerations:">Binary.</t>

    <t hangText="Interoperability considerations:">As was noted in the first paragraph
    of the "Security considerations" section, the same font
      format can be used to encode fonts supporting different types of outlines and/or text shaping and
      layout mechanisms. Existing font rendering engine implementations may not be able to process some
      of the particular layout table formats, and downloading a font resource that contains unsupported
      text shaping mechanism would result in inability of applications to display text properly.
      Therefore, it would be extremely useful to clearly identify the supported text shaping and layout
      data within a font using an optional parameter, and allow applications to make decisions about
      downloading a particular font resource sooner.
      Please note that as new text shaping mechanisms may be defined in the future, the set of allowed
      values for the optional parameter defined by this section may be extended.</t>

    <t hangText="Published specification:">ISO/IEC 14496-22 "Open Font Format" (OFF)
    specification <xref target="ISO.14496-22.2015"/> being developed by ISO/IEC SC29/WG11.</t>

    <t hangText="Applications that use this media type:">Any and all applications that are able to create, edit or display textual media content.</t>

  <t hangText="Additional information:">

  <list style="hanging">

      <t hangText="Magic number(s):">The TrueType fonts and OFF / OpenType fonts containing TrueType outlines should use 0x00010000
        as the 'sfnt' version number.</t>

      <t hangText="File extension(s):">Font file extensions used for TrueType / OFF /
      OpenType fonts: .ttf, .otf<vspace blankLines="1" />
      Typically, .ttf extension is only used for fonts containing TrueType outlines, while .otf
        extension may be used for any OpenType/OFF font, either with TrueType or CFF outlines.</t>

    <t hangText="Macintosh file type code(s):">(no code specified)</t>
    <t hangText="@font-face Format:">truetype</t>
    <t hangText="Fragment Identifiers">none.</t>
  </list>
  </t>

    <t hangText="Person &amp; email address to contact for further information:">Vladimir Levantovsky (vladimir.levantovsky@monotype.com).</t>

    <t hangText="Intended usage:">COMMON</t>

    <t hangText="Restrictions on usage:">None</t>

    <t hangText="Author:">The ISO/IEC 14496-22 "Open Font Format" specification is a
    product of the ISO/IEC JTC1 SC29/WG11.</t>

    <t hangText="Change controller:">The ISO/IEC has change control over this specification.</t>

  </list>
  </t>
  </section>



  <section title="OTF Font Type">
  <t>
  <list style="hanging">
    <t hangText="Type name:">font</t>

    <t hangText="Subtype name:">otf</t>

    <t hangText="Required parameters:">None.</t>

  <t hangText="Optional parameters">
  <list style="hanging">

    <t hangText="Name: outlines">Value: TTF, CFF, SVG<vspace blankLines="1" />

    This parameter can be used to specify the type of outlines provided by the font.
      Value "TTF" shall be used when a font resource contains glyph outlines in TrueType
      format, value "CFF" shall be used to identify fonts containing PostScript/CFF outlines,
      and value SVG shall be used to identify fonts that include SVG outlines. TTF, CFF
      or SVG outlines can be present in various combinations in the same font file, therefore,
      this optional parameter is a list containing one or more items, separated by commas, with
      optional whitespace. Order in the list is not significant.</t>
   </list>
   </t>

   <t hangText="Encoding considerations:">Binary.</t>

    <t hangText="Interoperability considerations:">As it was noted in the first paragraph
    of the "Security considerations" section, the
      same font format can be used to encode fonts with different types of glyph data represented
      as either TrueType, PostScript (CFF) or SVG outlines. Existing font rendering engines
      may not be able to process some of the particular outline formats, and downloading a font
      resource that contains unsupported glyph data format would result in inability of application
      to render and display text. Therefore, it would be extremely useful to clearly identify
      the format of the glyph outline data within a font using an optional parameter, and
      allow applications to make decisions about downloading a particular font resource sooner.
      Please note that as new outline formats may be defined in the future, the set of allowed
      values for the optional parameter defined in this section may be extended.</t>

    <t hangText="Published specification:">ISO/IEC 14496-22 "Open Font Format" (OFF)
    specification <xref target="ISO.14496-22.2015"/> being developed by ISO/IEC SC29/WG11.</t>

    <t hangText="Applications that use this media type:">Any and all applications that are able
    to create, edit or display textual media content.</t>

  <t hangText="Additional information:">

  <list style="hanging">

      <t hangText="Magic number(s):">The TrueType fonts and OFF / OpenType fonts containing
      TrueType outlines should use 0x00010000
        as the 'sfnt' version number.<vspace blankLines="1" />
      The OFF / OpenType fonts containing CFF outlines should use the tag 'OTTO' as 'sfnt' version number.
      There is no magic number for SVG outlines; these are always accompanied by either TrueType or CFF
      outlines and thus use the corresponding magic number.</t>

      <t hangText="File extension(s):">Font file extensions used for OFF /
      OpenType fonts: .ttf, .otf<vspace blankLines="1" />
      Typically, .ttf extension is only used for fonts containing TrueType outlines, while .otf
        extension can be used for any OpenType/OFF font, either with TrueType, CFF or SVG outlines.</t>

    <t hangText="Macintosh file type code(s):">(no code specified)</t>
    <t hangText="@font-face Format:">opentype</t>
    <!-- the @font-face format should be defined by reference to css3 fonts -->
    <t hangText="Fragment Identifiers">none.</t>
  </list>
  </t>

    <t hangText="Person &amp; email address to contact for further information:">Vladimir Levantovsky (vladimir.levantovsky@monotype.com).</t>

    <t hangText="Intended usage:">COMMON</t>

    <t hangText="Restrictions on usage:">None</t>

    <t hangText="Author:">The ISO/IEC 14496-22 "Open Font Format" specification is a product
    of the ISO/IEC JTC1 SC29/WG11.</t>

    <t hangText="Change controller:">The ISO/IEC has change control over this specification.</t>

  </list>
  </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Collection Font Type">
  <t>
  <list style="hanging">
    <t hangText="Type name:">font</t>

    <t hangText="Subtype name:">collection</t>

    <t hangText="Required parameters:">None.</t>

  <t hangText="Optional parameters">
  <list style="hanging">

    <t hangText="Name: outlines">Value: TTF, CFF, SVG<vspace blankLines="1" />

    This parameter can be used to specify the type of outlines provided by the font.
      Value "TTF" shall be used when a font resource contains glyph outlines in TrueType
      format, value "CFF" shall be used to identify fonts containing PostScript/CFF outlines,
      and value SVG shall be used to identify fonts that include SVG outlines. TTF, CFF
      or SVG outlines can be present in various combinations in the same font file, therefore,
      this optional parameter is a list containing one or more items, separated by commas, with
      optional whitespace. Order in the list is not significant.</t>
   </list>
   </t>

   <t hangText="Encoding considerations:">Binary.</t>

    <t hangText="Interoperability considerations:">As it was noted in the first paragraph
    of the "Security considerations" section, the
      same font format can be used to encode fonts with different types of glyph data represented
      as either TrueType, PostScript (CFF) or SVG outlines. Existing font rendering engines
      may not be able to process some of the particular outline formats, and downloading a font
      resource that contains unsupported glyph data format would result in inability of application
      to render and display text. Therefore, it would be extremely useful to clearly identify
      the format of the glyph outline data within a font using an optional parameter, and
      allow applications to make decisions about downloading a particular font resource sooner.
      Please note that as new outline formats may be defined in the future, the set of allowed
      values for the optional parameter defined in this section may be extended.</t>

    <t hangText="Published specification:">ISO/IEC 14496-22 "Open Font Format" (OFF)
    specification <xref target="ISO.14496-22.2015"/> being developed by ISO/IEC SC29/WG11.</t>

    <t hangText="Applications that use this media type:">Any and all applications that are able
    to create, edit or display textual media content.</t>

  <t hangText="Additional information:">

  <list style="hanging">

      <t hangText="Magic number(s):">The TrueType fonts and OFF / OpenType fonts containing
      TrueType outlines should use 0x00010000
        as the 'sfnt' version number.<vspace blankLines="1" />
      The OFF / OpenType fonts containing CFF outlines should use the tag 'OTTO' as 'sfnt' version number.
      There is no magic number for SVG outlines; these are always accompanied by either TrueType or CFF
      outlines and thus use the corresponding magic number.</t>

      <t hangText="File extension(s):">Font file extensions used for OFF /
      TrueType and OpenType fonts: .ttc </t>

    <t hangText="Macintosh file type code(s):">(no code specified)</t>
    <t hangText="@font-face Format:">collection</t>
    <t hangText="Fragment Identifiers">A positive integer. For example, #2 refers to the second font
    in the collection. If a fragment is not specified, it is the same as #1 i.e. the first font
    in the collection.</t>
  </list>
  </t>

    <t hangText="Person &amp; email address to contact for further information:">Vladimir Levantovsky (vladimir.levantovsky@monotype.com).</t>

    <t hangText="Intended usage:">COMMON</t>

    <t hangText="Restrictions on usage:">None</t>

    <t hangText="Author:">The ISO/IEC 14496-22 "Open Font Format" specification is a product
    of the ISO/IEC JTC1 SC29/WG11.</t>

    <t hangText="Change controller:">The ISO/IEC has change control over this specification.</t>

  </list>
  </t>
  </section>


  <section title="WOFF 1.0">
  <t>
  <list style="hanging">

    <t hangText="Type name:">font</t>

    <t hangText="Subtype name:">woff</t>

    <t hangText="Required parameters:">None.</t>

    <t hangText="Optional parameters:">None.</t>

   <t hangText="Encoding considerations:">Binary.</t>

    <t hangText="Interoperability considerations:">None. </t>

    <t hangText="Published specification:">This media type registration updates the WOFF specification
    <xref target="W3C.REC-WOFF-20121213"/> at W3C.</t>
      <!-- We should errata WOFF 1.0
      to note that the registration has been changed. -->

    <t hangText="Applications that use this media type:">WOFF is used by Web browsers, often
    in conjunction with HTML and CSS.</t>

  <t hangText="Additional information:">
  <list style="hanging">
    <t hangText="Magic number(s):">The signature field in the WOFF header MUST
    contain the "magic number" 0x774F4646 ('wOFF')</t>
    <t hangText="File extension(s):">woff</t>
    <t hangText="Macintosh file type code(s):">(no code specified)</t>
    <t hangText="Macintosh Universal Type Identifier code:"><spanx style="verb">org.w3c.woff</spanx> </t>
    <t hangText="@font-face Format:">woff</t>
    <t hangText="Fragment Identifiers:">none.</t>
    <t hangText="Deprecated Alias:">The existing registration application/font-woff is 
    deprecated in favor of font/woff.</t>
  </list>
  </t>

    <t hangText="Person &amp; email address to contact for further information:">Chris Lilley (www-font@w3.org).</t>

    <t hangText="Intended usage:">COMMON</t>

    <t hangText="Restrictions on usage:">None</t>

    <t hangText="Author:">The WOFF specification is a work product of the World Wide Web
    Consortium's WebFonts Working Group.</t>

    <t hangText="Change controller:">The W3C has change control over this specification.</t>

  </list>
  </t>
  </section>

<!-- what type for Collections, and do we define the fragment syntax to refer to individual fonts in the collection here? -->


  <section title="WOFF 2.0">
  <t>
  <list style="hanging">
    <t hangText="Type name:">font</t>

    <t hangText="Subtype name:">woff2</t>

    <t hangText="Required parameters:">None.</t>

    <t hangText="Optional parameters:">None.</t>

   <t hangText="Encoding considerations:">Binary.</t>

    <t hangText="Interoperability considerations:">WOFF 2.0 is an improvement on WOFF 1.0. The
    two formats have different Internet Media Types, different @font-face formats, and may be
    used in parallel. </t>

    <t hangText="Published specification:">This media type registration is extracted from the
    WOFF 2.0 specification <xref target="W3C.WD-WOFF2-20150414"/> at W3C.</t>

    <t hangText="Applications that use this media type:">WOFF 2.0 is used by Web browsers,
    often in conjunction with HTML and CSS.</t>

  <t hangText="Additional information:">

  <list style="hanging">
    <t hangText="Magic number(s):">The signature field in the WOFF header MUST contain the
    "magic number" 0x774F4632 ('wOF2')</t>
    <t hangText="File extension(s):">woff2</t>
    <t hangText="Macintosh file type code(s):">(no code specified)</t>
    <t hangText="Macintosh Universal Type Identifier code:"><spanx style="verb">org.w3c.woff2</spanx> </t>
    <t hangText="@font-face Format:">woff2</t>
    <t hangText="Fragment Identifiers">Optional, for collections encoded as WOFF 2.0. A positive integer.
    For example, #2 refers to the second font
    in the collection. If a fragment is not specified, it is the same as #1 i.e. the first font
    in the collection (or the only font, if it is not a collection). If a fragment is specified, and
    the WOFF does not encode a collection, the fragment is ignored.</t>
  </list>
  </t>

    <t hangText="Person &amp; email address to contact for further information:">Chris Lilley (www-font@w3.org).</t>

    <t hangText="Intended usage:">COMMON</t>

    <t hangText="Restrictions on usage:">None</t>

    <t hangText="Author:">The WOFF2 specification is a work product of the World Wide Web
    Consortium's WebFonts Working Group.</t>

    <t hangText="Change controller:">The W3C has change control over this specification.</t>

  </list>
  </t>

   </section>
   </section>
  </section>

   <section title="New Registrations">
    <t>New font formats should be registered using the online form <xref target="Media-Type-Registration"/>. 
    RFC 6838 <xref target="RFC6838"/> should be consulted on registration procedures. In particular
    the font specification must be freely available and the ABNF must be followed. Also,
    an @font-face format should be supplied and,
    if used, a definition of the fragment identifier syntax for the new type.</t>
   </section>
</middle>
<back>
	<references  title='Normative References'>
		<reference anchor="RFC2119" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119"><front><title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title><author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="S. Bradner"><organization/></author><date year="1997" month="March"/><abstract><t>In many standards track documents several words are used to signify the requirements in the specification.  These words are often capitalized. This document defines these words as they should be interpreted in IETF documents.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract></front><seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/><seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/><seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC2119"/></reference>
		<reference  anchor='RFC6838' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6838'>
		  <front>
		  <title>Media Type Specifications and Registration Procedures</title>
		  <author initials='N.' surname='Freed' fullname='N. Freed'><organization /></author>
		  <author initials='J.' surname='Klensin' fullname='J. Klensin'><organization /></author>
		  <author initials='T.' surname='Hansen' fullname='T. Hansen'><organization /></author>
		  <date year='2013' month='January' />
		  <abstract><t>This document defines procedures for the specification and registration of media types for use in HTTP, MIME, and other Internet protocols.  This memo documents an Internet Best Current Practice.</t></abstract>
		  </front>
		  <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='13'/>
		  <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6838'/>
		  <seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC6838'/>
		</reference>
    	<reference anchor="W3C.CR-css-fonts-3-20131003" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/2013/CR-css-fonts-3-20131003"><front><title>CSS Fonts Module Level 3</title><author initials="J." surname="Daggett" fullname="John Daggett"><organization/></author><date month="October" day="3" year="2013"/>
    	<abstract><t>This CSS3 module describes how font properties are specified and how font resources are loaded dynamically. The contents of this specification are a consolidation of content previously divided into CSS3 Fonts and CSS3 Web Fonts modules. The description of font load events was moved into the CSS3 Font Load Events module. </t></abstract>
    	</front><seriesInfo name="World Wide Web Consortium CR" value="CR-css-fonts-3-20131003"/><format type="HTML" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/2013/CR-css-fonts-3-20131003"/>
		</reference>
		<reference anchor="ISO.14496-22.2015" target="http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c066391_ISO_IEC_14496-22_2015.zip">
<front>
<title>Coding of audio-visual objects Part 22: Open Font Format</title>
<author>
<organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization>
</author>
<date month="10" year="2015" />
<abstract><t>ISO/IEC 14496-22:2015 specifies the Open Font Format (OFF) specification, the TrueType™ and Compact Font Format (CFF) 
<xref target="cff-wiki"/> 
outline formats, and the TrueType hinting language. Many references to both TrueType and PostScript exist throughout this document, as Open Font Format fonts combine the two technologies</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="ISO" value="Standard 14496-22" />
</reference>
		<reference anchor="W3C.REC-WOFF-20121213" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/2012/REC-WOFF-20121213">
      <front><title>WOFF File Format 1.0</title>
      <author initials="J." surname="Kew" fullname="Jonathan Kew"><organization/></author>
      <author initials="T." surname="Leming" fullname="Tal Leming"><organization/></author>
      <author initials="E." surname="Blokland" fullname="Erik van Blokland"><organization/></author>
      <date month="December" day="13" year="2012"/>
		<abstract>
      <t>This document specifies the WOFF font packaging format. This format was designed to provide
      lightweight, easy-to-implement compression of font data, suitable for use with CSS @font-face rules.
      Any properly licensed TrueType/OpenType/Open Font Format file can be packaged in WOFF format for Web
      use. User agents decode the WOFF file to restore the font data such that it will display identically
      to the input font.</t>
      <t>The WOFF format also allows additional metadata to be attached to the file; this can be used
        by font designers or vendors to include licensing or other information, beyond that present in the
        original font. Such metadata does not affect the rendering of the font in any way, but may be displayed
        to the user on request.</t>
      <t>The WOFF format is not intended to replace other formats such as TrueType/OpenType/Open Font Format
        or SVG fonts, but provides an alternative solution for use cases where these formats may be less
        optimal, or where licensing considerations make their use less acceptable.</t>
      </abstract>
		</front>
    <seriesInfo name="World Wide Web Consortium Recommendation" value="REC-WOFF-20121213"/>
    <format type="HTML" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/2012/REC-WOFF-20121213"/>
  </reference>

		<reference anchor="W3C.WD-WOFF2-20150414" target="https://www.w3.org/TR/2016/CR-WOFF2-20160315/">
      <front><title>WOFF File Format 2.0</title>
      <author initials="V." surname="Levantovsky" fullname="Vladimir Levantovsky"><organization/></author>
      <author initials="R." surname="Levien" fullname="Raph Levien"><organization/></author>
      <date month="March" day="15" year="2016"/>
		<abstract><t>Based on experience with WOFF 1.0, which is widely deployed, this specification was
      developed to provide improved compression and thus lower use of network bandwidth, while still
      allowing fast decompression even on mobile devices. This is achieved by combining a content-aware
      preprocessing step and improved entropy coding, compared to the Flate compression used in
      WOFF 1.0.</t>
    </abstract>
		</front><seriesInfo name="World Wide Web Consortium WD" value="WD-WOFF2-20150414"/>
    <format type="HTML" target="https://www.w3.org/TR/2016/CR-WOFF2-20160315/"/></reference>

	</references>
	<references  title='Informative References'>
    <reference anchor="cff-wiki" target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PostScript_fonts#Compact_Font_Format">
        <front>
          <title>CFF</title>
          <author><organization/></author>
          <date/>
          <abstract><t>Compact Font Format (also known as CFF font format, Type 2 font 
          format, or CFF/Type 2 font format) is 
          a lossless compaction of the Type 1 format using Type 2 charstrings.
          The PostScript or Type 1 flavor of OpenType fonts, also called 
          OpenType CFF, contains glyph outlines and hints in a CFF table</t></abstract>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="opentype-wiki" target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenType">
        <front>
          <title>OpenType</title>
          <author><organization/></author>
          <date/>
          <abstract><t>OpenType is a format for scalable computer fonts. It was built 
          on its predecessor TrueType, retaining TrueType's basic structure and adding 
          many intricate data structures for prescribing typographic behavior. </t></abstract>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="postscript-wiki" target="">
        <front>
          <title>PostScript</title>
          <author><organization/></author>
          <date/>
          <abstract><t>PostScript (PS) is a computer language for creating vector 
          graphics. It is a dynamically typed, concatenative programming language and 
          was created at Adobe Systems by John Warnock, Charles Geschke, Doug Brotz, 
          Ed Taft and Bill Paxton from 1982 to 1984.</t></abstract>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="truetype-wiki" target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TrueType">
        <front>
          <title>TrueType</title>
          <author><organization/></author>
          <date/>
          <abstract><t>TrueType is an outline font standard developed by Apple and Microsoft 
          in the late 1980s as a competitor to Adobe's Type 1 fonts used in 
          PostScript. </t></abstract>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="svg-wiki" target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scalable_Vector_Graphics">
        <front>
          <title>SVG</title>
          <author><organization/></author>
          <date/>
          <abstract><t>Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) is an XML-based vector image 
          format for two-dimensional graphics with support for interactivity and animation. 
          The SVG specification is an open standard developed by the World Wide Web 
          Consortium (W3C) since 1999.</t></abstract>
        </front>
      </reference>
    	<reference anchor="HTTP-Archive-Trends"
        target="http://httparchive.org/trends.php?s=All&amp;minlabel=Nov+15+2010&amp;maxlabel=Feb+15+2015#perFonts">
    		<front>
    			<title>HTTP Archive trend analysis</title>
          <author initials="D." surname="Kuetell" fullname="David Kuetell"><organization/></author>
    			<date month="March" year="2015"/>
    			<abstract><t>
    			Analysis of the Alexa top 480K websites, from Nov 15 2010 to
    			Feb 15 2015. It shows a steady rise in the number of sites using webfonts,
    			from 1% in 2010 to 50% in 2015.
    			</t></abstract>
    		</front>
    	</reference>
    	<reference anchor="Font-Media-Type-Analysis" target="http://goo.gl/zbDhUN">
    		<front>
    			<title>Web Font Media Type (mime type) Analysis 2015</title>
          <author initials="D." surname="Kuetell" fullname="David Kuetell"><organization/></author>
    			<date year="2015"/>
    			<abstract><t>
    			Adoption rate of registered media types for TrueType, OpenType and WOFF
    			fonts (in the application tree) is extremely low, ranging from 1% to 0.07%.
    			In practice, a wide range of unregistered types is observed, including significant
    			use (90.8%, for WOFF) of the non-existent font top-level type. This contrasts
    			with more than 90% adoption rate for PNG, GIF, and JPEG which have intuitive
    			Media Types in the image tree.
    			</t></abstract>
    		</front>
    	</reference>
      <reference anchor="W3C-tlt" target="https://www.w3.org/Fonts/WG/track/actions/164">
        <front>
          <title>ACTION-164: Bring widely used top-level-type to w3c-ietf liaison</title>
          <author><organization>W3C</Organization> </author>
          <date year="2015"/>
          <abstract><t>Following discussion at several phone calls and face to face meetings, 
          the W3C WebFonts Working group decided that the widely used but unregistered font/* top-level type
          should be standardized, and created this action item to track it.</t></abstract>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="Media-Type-Registration" target="http://www.iana.org/form/media-types">
        <front>
        <title>Application for a Media Type</title>
        <author><organization>IANA</organization></author>
        <date/> <!-- not sure what date to put for a form -->
        <abstract><t>Application form for new Internet Media Types.</t></abstract>
        </front>
    </reference>
    </references>
</back>
    </rfc>
